There's one more thing you can do to protect yourself from experiencing the symptoms of Alzheimer's, even if you have the full-blown disease pathology ablaze in your brain. It has to do with neural plasticity and cognitive reserve. Remember, the experience of having Alzheimer's is ultimately a result of losing synapses. The average brain has over a hundred trillion synapses, which is fantastic; we've got a lot to work with. And this isn't a static number. We gain and lose synapses all the time, through a process called neural plasticity. Every time we learn something new, we are creating and strengthening new neural connections, new synapses. In the Nun Study, 678 nuns, all over the age of 75 when the study began, were followed for more than two decades. They were regularly given physical checkups and cognitive tests, and when they died, their brains were all donated for autopsy. In some of these brains, scientists discovered something surprising. Despite the presence of plaques and tangles and brain shrinkage -- what appeared to be unquestionable Alzheimer's -- the nuns who had belonged to these brains showed no signs of having the disease while they were alive. How can this be? We think it's because these nuns had a high level of cognitive reserve, which is a way of saying that they had more functional synapses. People who have more years of formal education, who have a high degree of literacy, who engage regularly in mentally stimulating activities, all have more cognitive reserve. They have an abundance and a redundancy in neural connections. So even if they have a disease like Alzheimer's compromising some of their synapses, they've got many extra backup connections, and this buffers them from noticing that anything is amiss. Let's imagine a simplified example. Let's say you only know one thing about a subject. Let's say it's about me. You know that Lisa Genova wrote "Still Alice," and that's the only thing you know about me. You have that single neural connection, that one synapse. Now imagine you have Alzheimer's. You have plaques and tangles and inflammation and microglia devouring that synapse. Now when someone asks you, "Hey, who wrote 'Still Alice?'" you can't remember, because that synapse is either failing or gone. You've forgotten me forever. But what if you had learned more about me? Let's say you learned four things about me. Now imagine you have Alzheimer's, and three of those synapses are damaged or destroyed. You still have a way to detour the wreckage. You can still remember my name. So we can be resilient to the presence of Alzheimer's pathology through the recruitment of yet-undamaged pathways. And we create these pathways, this cognitive reserve, by learning new things. Ideally, we want these new things to be as rich in meaning as possible, recruiting sight and sound and associations and emotion. So this really doesn't mean doing crossword puzzles. You don't want to simply retrieve information you've already learned, because this is like traveling down old, familiar streets, cruising neighborhoods you already know. You want to pave new neural roads. Building an Alzheimer's-resistant brain means learning to speak Italian, meeting new friends, reading a book, or listening to a great TED Talk. And if, despite all of this, you are someday diagnosed with Alzheimer's, there are three lessons I've learned from my grandmother and the dozens of people I've come to know living with this disease. Diagnosis doesn't mean you're dying tomorrow. Keep living. You won't lose your emotional memory. You'll still be able to understand love and joy. You might not remember what I said five minutes ago, but you'll remember how I made you feel. And you are more than what you can remember. Thank you. (Applause)
Hay algo más que pueden hacer para protegerte de los síntomas del alzhéimer, aunque su cerebro parezca tener un cuadro patológico completo. Tiene que ver con la neuroplasticidad y la reserva cognitiva. Recuerden, la experiencia de tener alzhéimer es en última instancia el resultado de perder sinapsis. En promedio, un cerebro tiene más de 100 billones de sinapsis, lo que es fantástico; tenemos mucho con qué trabajar. Y no es un número estático. Ganamos y perdemos sinapsis todo el tiempo, mediante un proceso llamado neuroplasticidad. Cada vez que aprendemos algo nuevo, creamos y fortalecemos conexiones neuronales nuevas, sinapsis nuevas. En el 'Estudio de las monjas', 678 monjas, todas sobre los 75 años, al inicio del estudio, fueron observadas por más de dos décadas. Se expusieron regularmente a exámenes físicos y cognitivos, y, al morir, donaron sus cerebros para una autopsia. Los científicos descubrieron algo sorprendente en algunos cerebros. A pesar de la presencia de placas, ovillos y atrofia cerebral, lo que aparentaba ser alzhéimer sin lugar a dudas, las monjas a las que pertenecían los cerebros no demostraron síntomas de esta enfermedad mientras vivían. ¿Cómo puede ser? Pensamos que se debe a que las monjas tenían un alto grado de reserva cognitiva, lo que significa que tenían más sinapsis funcionales. Las personas con más años de educación formal, con un alto grado de alfabetismo, que suelen involucrarse en actividades que estimulan la mente, todas tienen una reserva cognitiva mayor. Tienen una abundancia y una redundancia de conexiones neurales. Así que, aunque tengan una enfermedad como el alzhéimer que comprometa algunas de las sinapsis, tienen muchas conexiones de respaldo adicionales, y esto las protege de darse cuenta de que algo anda mal. Pongamos un ejemplo simplificado. Digamos que solo saben una cosa de un tema. Digamos que es sobre mí. Saben que Lisa Genova escribió "Siempre Alice", y es lo único que saben sobre mí. Tienen esa única conexión neural, una sola sinapsis. Ahora imaginemos que tienen alzhéimer. Tienen placas, ovillos, inflamación y microglía devorando la sinapsis. Ahora cuando alguien les pregunta, "Oye, ¿quién escribió 'Siempre Alice'?", no se acuerdan, porque esa sinapsis está fallando o desapareció. Me han olvidado para siempre. Pero ¿qué sucede si aprenden más de mí? Digamos que saben cuatro cosas sobre mí. Ahora imaginemos que tienen alzhéimer, y tres de esas sinapsis están dañadas o destruidas. Aún tienen una manera de darle la vuelta. Aún puedes recordar mi nombre. Podemos resistir la presencia de una patología de alzhéimer mediante el desarrollo de rutas en buen estado. Y creamos estas rutas, esta reserva cognitiva, al aprender cosas nuevas. Idealmente, se quiere que estas novedades sean lo más ricas en significado posible, involucrado la vista, la audición, las asociaciones y las emociones. En realidad, esto no se refiere a hacer crucigramas. No quieren simplemente recuperar información ya aprendida, porque esto es como viajar por calles ya familiares, cruzar vecindarios que ya conocen. Quieren crear nuevas carreteras neuronales. Fortalecer el cerebro contra el alzhéimer significa aprender a hablar italiano, hacer nuevas amistades, leer un libro, o escuchar una gran charla de TED. Y si, a pesar de todo esto, algún día les diagnostican con alzhéimer, hay tres lecciones que aprendí de mi abuela y de docenas de personas que he conocido que viven con la enfermedad. El diagnóstico no quiere decir que morirán mañana. Continúa su vida. No perderán su memoria sentimental. Aún podrán sentir amor y felicidad. Tal vez no recuerden lo que dije hace cinco minutos, pero recordarán cómo les hice sentir. Y somos más de lo que recordamos. Gracias. (Aplausos)